Guide to the Herbert Nanney Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Herbert Nanney papers
1924-2005
SC0920
Nanney, Herbert, 1918-1996
4 Linear feet
Programs, news clippings, correspondence, photographs, audio recordings, music scores, and other materials which document Herbert Nanney's tenure as Stanford University professor of music and university organist.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
Collection is open for research; materials must be requested at least 24 hours in advance of intended use.
Biography / Administrative History
Herbert Boswell Nanney, university organist and professor of music at Stanford University, was born in Whittier, California in 1918. He began piano lessons at the age of five, and studied organ under UCLA's Alexander Schreiner while a high school student. Nanney received his A.B. in Music from Whittier College in 1940, an Artist's Diploma from the Curtis Institute of Music in Philadelphia in 1947, and his M.A. from Stanford in 1951.
Nanney first came to Stanford shortly after receiving his A.B., serving as assistant to university organist William D. Allen. He left Stanford to attend the Curtis Institute of Music in 1941. In August 1942 he was inducted into the Army. While stationed in Paris from 1944-1945, Nanney studied organ with Marcel Dupre at the Paris Conservatory of Music and was organist at the American Cathedral.
After his return from Europe, Nanney served as organist and choir director for churches in southern California and Philadelphia before returning to Stanford in 1947 as university organist and a member of the music faculty. In the years that followed he traveled regularly to lecture and perform, and was instrumental in the planning and construction of the Fisk-Nanney organ in Memorial Church, which was dedicated in 1984.
Nanney's 1985 retirement was celebrated with a series of concerts on campus, at which 30 of his former students played the works of Bach. He remained in the Bay Area until his death in 1996.
Scope and Content of Collection
Programs and news clippings related to performances by Nanney comprise the bulk of these papers. For preservation reasons, clippings on newsprint have been placed at the end of each folder and are segregated from other documents with acid-free paper. Also included are several folders of clippings, programs, and other documents related to the construction of the Fisk-Nanney organ at Stanford University's Memorial Church. There are also several tributes to Nanney, including congratulatory letters compiled and presented to him at the time of his retirement; a memorial service address by James Welch; and a program and an original composition from an honorary concert presented by the San Jose Chapter of the American Guild of Organists.
Many of the programs, news clippings, and congratulatory letters were originally located in scrapbooks. Due to preservation concerns these items were detached from their scrapbook pages and placed in acid-free folders. Folder titles indicate items that were originally found in scrapbooks.
Other correspondence is sparse and consists largely of letters to Nanney from his parents. Two items of particular interest are a 1945 letter of reference from prominent French organist Marcel Dupre and a 1953 letter from Vice President Richard Nixon in response to Nanney's inquiry about the position of Organist and Choirmaster at West Point's Cadet Chapel.
There are two recordings of works by Nanney: a CD-R copy of a 1956 baroque music performance in Memorial Church and an LP of Nanney s performance at the 1963 Far West Regional Convention of the American Guild of Organists. The papers also include several original compositions by Nanney, including his Sonata in E Minor for pipe organ and The Creation: A Sacred Cantata for Chorus, Soprano and Baritone Soloists, Full Orchestra, and Organ.
Most of the photographs in box 1 are posed portraits of Nanney, but there are a few images of the Memorial Church organ as well as several individual and group photographs of others.
The papers were donated to the Stanford University Archives by James Welch, a former Nanney student. Welch's notes on the papers are included in box 5, folder 12. There is also a transcript of Welch's 1991 interview with Nanney, a recording of the interview on audiocassette, and a copy of Welch's piece on Nanney for Stanford magazine's January/February 2003 "The Teacher Who Changed My Life" feature.
Access Terms
Stanford University. Department of Music.; Stanford University. Memorial Church; Organists--California.
Collection Contents
- American Guild of Organists San Jose chapter recital in honor of Nanney, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Biographical information, 1954, 1992, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1943-1947, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1963-1964, 1976-1979, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Fisk Organ, 1979-1984 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Fisk Organ, 1979-1984 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Fisk Organ, 1979-1984 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Music, Fantasie, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Music, Fantasie in C Minor, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Music, Holy Holy Holy, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Music, Jehovah Is My Keeper, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Music, Musical Setting for Macbeth, Act IV, Scene I, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Music, Variations Written in Paris, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Music, We Limit Not the Truth of God, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Photographs, portraits of Nanney [16 items; several are duplicates], circa 1930s-1980s (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Photographs, portraits of Nanney in Army uniform [5 items; 2 are duplicates], circa 1942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Photographs, Nanney posed at organ [18 items; several duplicates], circa 1940s-1980s (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Proof sheets, photographs of Nanney posed at organ [3 items], undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Photographs, (Memorial Church?) organ [3 items], undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Proof sheet, photographs of organ, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Photograh, Nanney with parents and sister?, circa 1920s (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Photograph, Nanney as child with band, circa late 1920s-early 1930s (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Photograph, Nanney at piano with chorus, circa 1940s-1950s (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Photograph, Nanney at organ console with five singers, circa 1950s (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Photograph, Nanney at piano with man playing guitar, circa 1950s-1960s (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Photograph, Nanney at organ console with two men, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Photographs, Nanney with two men in Memorial Church, establishment of Herbert Nanney Scholarship in Organ [4 items], 1987 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Photograph, Nanney and wife with one other couple outside Memorial Church, circa 1980s (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Photographs, Nanney with former students who performed in Bach tribute [2 identical items], 1985 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Photograph, Alexander Schreiner posed at organ, signed to Nanney, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Group photograph of men and women in army uniforms, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Group photograph of San Francisco Bank Junior Choral Group, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Photograph, Sandor Salgo (professor of music at Stanford), undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Photograph, unidentified man at organ with radio microphone, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Programs and clippings, 1935-1936 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Programs and clippings, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Programs and clippings, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Programs and clippings, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Programs and clippings, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Programs and clippings, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Programs and clippings, 1942-1943 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Programs and clippings, 1944-1945 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Programs and clippings, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Programs and clippings, 1947-1948 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Programs and clippings, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Programs and clippings, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Programs and clippings, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Programs and clippings, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Programs and clippings, 1954-1955 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Programs and clippings, 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Programs and clippings, 1958-1959 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Programs and clippings, 1960-1962 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Programs and clippings, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Programs and clippings, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Programs and clippings, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Programs and clippings, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Programs and clippings, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Programs and clippings, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Programs and clippings, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Programs and clippings, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Programs and clippings, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Programs and clippings, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Programs and clippings, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Programs and clippings, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Programs and clippings, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Programs and clippings, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Programs and clippings, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Programs and clippings, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Programs and clippings, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Programs and clippings, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Programs and clippings, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Programs and clippings, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Programs and clippings, 1983-1988 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Programs and clippings, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Programs and clippings [from scrapbook], 1924-1930 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Programs and clippings [from scrapbook], 1931-1932 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Programs and clippings [from scrapbook], 1933-1934 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Programs and clippings [from scrapbook], 1935 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Programs and clippings [from scrapbook], 1936 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Programs and clippings [from scrapbook], 1936 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Programs and clippings [from scrapbook], 1937 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Programs and clippings [from scrapbook], 1937 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Programs and clippings [from scrapbook], 1938 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Programs and clippings [from scrapbook], 1938 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Programs and clippings [from scrapbook], 1939-1940 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Programs and clippings [from scrapbook], 1947-1948 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Programs and clippings [from scrapbook], 1947-1948 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Programs and clippings [from scrapbook], 1949 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Programs and clippings [from scrapbook], 1950-1953 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Programs, postcards, and ephemera from France, 1944-1945 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Programs, postcards, and ephemera from France, 1944-1945 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Retirement, 1984-1985 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Retirement, letters from and photographs of students [from scrapbook], 1985 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Retirement, letters from colleagues and photographs from party [from scrapbook], 1985 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Welch, James, interview of Nanney. Approximate running time: 1 hour, 23 minutes], 1991; 1 optical disc(s) (CD-R) (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Welch, James, writings on Nanney, 1996, 2003, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Recording of baroque music concert, Memorial Hall [includes insert with complete program listed], 1956 Nov 18; 1 optical disc(s) (CD-R) (Box 5)
- Oversize retirement card with watercolor sketch of Nanney at organ, 1985
- The Creation: A Sacred Cantata for Chorus, Soprano and Baritone Soloists, Full Orchestra, and Organ, oversize score, undated
- Nanney's performance at the Far West Regional Convention of the American Guild of Organists, 1963; 1 phonograph record(s)
- Sonata in E Minor, 1939-1940 (Folder 1)
- Adagio from Sonata in E Minor, Morningstar Music Publishers, 1993 (Folder 1)
- Sonata in E Minor, carbons, 1939-1940 (Folder 2)
- Oversize photograph of Nanney, circa late 1920s-early 1930s (Folder 3)
- Poster, Recital on the Handel Organ of Holy Trinity Gosport by Herbert Nanney, 1981 (Folder 3)
- Retirement card with calligraphy on parchment, 1985 (Folder 3)